Guide to the Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection. 1960-1978
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- 1968, Compact disc (Disc 4)
  - "Copy of tape made at Cliff's home. Phil, Pem, Seline, Bo, Cliff" 1968 (Track 5)
    A man reads what seems to be an article about Philo Farnsworth and others working for his company. It isn't clear where the article is from. Everyone in the room is amused by the article.
    Once again, various people talk over each other and only small snippets of conversation can be heard.
    The audio then is turned off for a minute or so.
    Once the audio comes back on it's difficult to hear what is being said.
- 1968, 1969, Compact disc (Disc 5)
  - "Copy of Tape made at Cliff's home. Phil, Pem, Seline, Bo, Cliff" 1968 pt. 2 (Track 5)
    A man tells a story, but it is difficult to make out exactly what he is saying. The rest of this track is difficult to hear.
  - "Copy of tape made at Cliff's home. Phil, Pem, Seline, Bo, Cliff" 1968 pt. 2, side 2. (Track 5)
    Difficult to hear what is said.
  - "PTFA's Director's Meeting" 1969 (Track 6)
    Man speaking says that the meeting has been called because they need to talk about demonstrating a product that they are working on for another company (Black Mountain?). This company will bring their metallurgist, an attorney, and the division expert to attend the demonstration.
    He talks about the specifications for the product, specifically the metals involved in the tube and some of the processes involved with the metals.
    This section stretches on and is quite technical. The people in the meeting talk a little bit about sourcing some of the materials as well.
    The people in the meeting vote on electing Dewey Bluke (Bluth? Unsure on spelling) to VP and senior member of the associates. Ralph Maxwell is up for becoming an interim associate when he has enough education, but it seems the vote is postponed because of some confusion over bylaws relating to being an associate. This not totally clear. It appears Ralph will retire when his son begins to work, but still be employed as a consultant.
    They talk about allowing associates to purchase stock at par value, which they believe is a very good deal. Each associate must own at least one share of the stock.
    They are about to open up an IPO to the public, and discuss the price that they feel they should list it at, and at what point they will want to cut off stock purchases.
- 1970, Compact disc (Disc 6)
  - "Interview with Frank Smith at our home in Holladay, Ut." 2/6/70 Side 1, 1970 (Track 7)
    Frank Smith is interviewing Philo Farnsworth.
    Philo says that he knew at six that he would be an inventor. It's difficult to hear what he says sometimes as he speaks very softly and not very well.
    He describes an invention that he made at eight years old, but it is very difficult to hear exactly what he says.
    Mr. Farnsworth says he knew Justin Tollman, the brother of a principle at an Idaho high school that Philo attended. He says that Mr. Tollman had notes that Philo had made and kept them for fifteen years. He tutored Philo extremely frequently throughout school.
    In San Francisco, he created the first electronic television transmitter tube. Sound comes in and out from the tape for a little bit.
    He was told by a Caltech engineer that he stood as much a chance as a drip of ice on a red hot stove.
    It took about a year to get a television picture that was as good as the average home set during 1970.
    Philo owns a patent for horizontal and vertical synchronization that he believes is extremely important because it removes the horizontal lines from the picture. He says it is still being used in the exact same form as of the time of the interview.
    He owned at some point 165 US patents, unsure if he still owns this many. RCA attempted to sue him for some of the patents but he did not lose a single case.
    He developed a serum for hemolytic streptococcus while working with the University of Pennsylvania, which had been incurable previously. He says that the loss of his second son to hemolytic streptococcus motivated him to work in the field of medicine.
    He believes that television is beginning to hurt the peripheral vision of children and envisions a television experience in which you would simply be able to walk into the virtual projection rather than watching it on a screen.
    He thanks Roy N. Bishop, W.W. Crocker, Joseph Feagen (unsure on spelling), because they were his initial backers in his research and development of the television.
  - "Interview with Frank Smith at our home in Holladay, Ut." 2/6/70 Side 2., 1970 (Track 7)
    His wife continues to reflect on the time that they spent working on the television. She says his charisma and self-confidence were infectious and helped to draw financial backers.
    She talks about his hope to help the world with his invention of a fusion energy source, specifically those who are in worse positions. He believes that this invention specifically could help to provide food in places that struggle to grow it.
    His wife says that they moved to Fort Wayne, Indiana because at that point there were not guidelines in place that allowed for enough airwaves available for commercial television to have legs at that point.
    They needed money while that was worked out, so they helped to manufacture radios. They left there in either late 1939 or early 1940 to allow Philo to regain his health in Maine.
    In Maine he worked on lumber production for World War 2, as well as fusion technology, and even some work on jet planes.
    They moved to Salt Lake City in 1968 because KSL and David McKay wanted to make a documentary on Philo.
    During his portion of the interview, Philo had just recovered from Pneumonia and was under heavy medication. He struggled to talk largely because of that.
- 1974, Compact disc (Disc 7)
  - "Cy Day" 7/74 Side 1., 1974 (Track 8)
    "The Story of Television" by George Everson came out in 1949. Philo's wife tells the story of the first time he had health problems. They were visiting the French Riviera at the time and had to stay for a few weeks because the doctor wouldn't release him. George was unhappy about this and the original manuscript reflected this.
    His wife and the older man she is talking with discuss a few of his old friends and what has happened to them. The man she is talking to is difficult to understand and sounds very old.
    They talk about his work ethic, how he was to work with, what he expected of others, and things like that for a little while.
  - "Cy Day" 7/74 Side 2., 1974 (Track 8)
    A woman is now being interviewed. She graduated from University in 1943 and talks about her experiences with the first company she worked for K-part Farnsworth Television company.
    She talks about some half tubes that she had made while working specifically with Philo, which seemed to be for demonstration not for any practical purpose. They had to be made by hand.
    They talk about the difficulty of continuing Philo's fusion research now that he has died. They say the math is too complicated and most people wouldn't be able to understand it very well.
    They talk about how sharp Philo was and how it sometimes made his conversation difficult to follow because he would shift gears so quickly.
    Philo's wife tells a story about how RCA drove a man to jump out of a window because of lawsuits over a patent.
    His wife talks about his obsession with the future and how she found it impressive but also believes that it cut his life short.
- 1974, Compact disc (Disc 8)
  - "Cy Day" 7/74 Side 1., 1974 (Track 9)
    Philo's wife says that his nervous breakdown in 1939 was brought on by the extra responsibility when the firm he was working with became a manufacturer as well as a research firm, giving him engineering duties in addition to what he had already been doing.
    They discuss the use of tubes in various applications, including talk of using it in a radio control tower at an airport for quite a while.
    After that discussion they mostly talk about people who worked with Phil and what has happened to them since.
  - "Cy Day" 7/74 Side 2., 1974 (Track 9)
    She tells a story about how their car had died at the airport and because Ed White knew the airport manager so they were able to jump their car even though it was about 1 AM.
    They talk about all the times that Farnsworth's company changed names.
    They again talk about different people who worked for the company as well as stories working for the company.
    She says that at one point the lab they worked in became contaminated with radioactive particles and they went on vacation for three weeks while it was being cleaned.
- 1974, Compact disc (Disc 9)
  - "Gene and Jim – Steve Blaising" 1974 Side 1. (Track 10)
    He began working at the company just before the United States entered World War 2. He took motion pictures of his lab.
    They talk about Phil's love of baseball and listening to it on the radio.
    He recounts seeing color TV for the first time at the company in 1941 which was pretty much unheard of at that time.
    They talk about Phil's procrastination when it comes to signing books. He says that Phil left the book on his desk in his room for six weeks before it was finally returned. Phil never read the book because it wasn't entirely complimentary.
    He tells a story of when they discovered their fusion experiment was working and the joy that they all felt when they thought they had proved it was working. A graduate student then pointed out that it was not working as they had hoped and in the end the project was unsuccessful.
    They talk about Phil's impatience with the publishing process and his wife tells a story of Phil talking to Albert Einstein, who insisted that Phil push forward his math on fusion for publication. Phil instead tried to make his fusion energy system work, and then have someone else go through the process of getting the math to be published and publicly accepted. Unfortunately, he was unable to complete this project before he died.
  - "Gene and Jim – Steve Blaising, Jim Hiney" 1974 Side 1. (Track 10)
    Gene first met Phil in 1959 while looking for extra overtime work. He came over in the early afternoon and didn't leave until four thirty AM.
    Jim first met Phil in 1961 because a drafter he had assigned to work with Phil left. He was given the opportunity after the first guy had left. Phil introduced himself to Jim after a few days of doing drafting work and Phil invited him into the basement to the lab.
    They didn't receive very much funding to work on the fusion project until either late 1959 or early 1960.
    One of them remembers receiving a call to come to Phil's house to work at around eleven PM.
    They talk about his work attitudes and his feeling that if you weren't enjoying your work you should find a new job.
    They talk about his assumption that everyone he employed was very smart and how it was both a good and bad thing.
- 1974, Compact disc (Disc 10)
  - "Gene and Jim – Steve Blaising" 1974 Side 2. (Track 10)
    After Phil died, one of them asked for money to continue to work on the experiment and ended up getting five thousand dollars. Their experiments were relatively successful and the next year they were able to obtain twenty eight thousand dollars. At this point in time, the work was only going on at BYU, Illinois, and Penn State.
    They say that at the end of Phil's life he was very determined to quickly make progress on his fusion research because he knew he didn't have too much longer to live.
    They tell a story of Phil cleaning out a boat that they all find very funny.
    He tells a story of a cookout right after Phil had some teeth pulled. His wife got his son a steak, and got baby food for Phil and they all laugh at the story.
    They talk about the difficulty of getting funding for some of Phil's projects because he often was doing things that went against what the people they were asking for funding had spent their lives working on and with.
- 1974, Compact disc (Disc 11)
  - "ITT East Gate Guard – Paul Redding" and "Don Carlos – tube dept." 1974 Side 1. (Track 11)
    She first speaks with Paul Redding. They talk about a few people that she can go see who used to work for the company when Philo was first starting it who would have worked with him.
    They talk about Phil's manners, she remarks that she had heard that he had raised his voice at work only twice in his life.
    She talks to Don Carlos, who is still working on tubes. From what is said it appears that they are in a factory or manufacturing facility of some sort as they talk.
    He tells her about a variety of different tubes that were manufactured for different specific purposes.
  - "ITT East Gate Guard – Paul Redding" and "Don Carlos – tube dept." 1974 Side 2. (Track 11)
    Mrs. Smith was a teacher at Eaglebrook. Phil's younger son recounts his experience, specifically his dislike of Eaglebrook and its practices. He said that he got through his first month at Eaglebrook by fantasizing about running away with a bag full of cookies.
    World War 2 ended the summer before he went to Eaglebrook, he was ten years old at the time.
    He tells a story of staying with his uncle and having someone from the FBI come to the door to ask about his uncle.
    Phil's wife tells a story about living in Maine and the suspicions of the local people that they were Nazi spies, then another story about the police in Hollywood suspecting they were running a distillery.
    She tells a story about when she was pregnant but didn't know it yet. She went to a doctor initially who misdiagnosed her as having a tumor, but a second doctor correctly found that she was actually just pregnant.
    He talks about losing all of his instruments when he and his brother shipped everything they owned to New York and when he got there he didn't have enough money to collect them.
    He says something that Phil said to him was to give yourself a chance to solve a difficult problem by going to a quiet place to work on it.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 12)
  - "At Cliff's house with Cliff, Arch, Harold, and Pem" 1/4/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 12)
    She says she is working on getting Phil's name in more history books because she is sad that her younger family will grow up with less evidence that he was so influential in the development of the television.
    Cliff says he is unsure exactly which tubes would have been older.
    Arch says that the techniques for glass blowing tubes were developed by Charlie Litten at Federal in about 1930 or 1931 and this allowed for the creation of large tubes for transmitters.
    He says that he began to work for Federal in 1929 but was laid off when the lab he was working in closed due to the great depression. He went to see Phil and began to work for him after that. They get into some of the more technical work that he spent time on during his early time with Phil's company.
    Harold says he joined Phil's company in the winter of 1935 just before 1936. He says that when Cliff picked him up from the depot after midnight they went to check out the lab before taking him home. He says that everyone except for the glass blowers were still at the lab and working.
    Phil's wife tells a story about hiring a nurse to run the clean room during World War 2. She says that a doctor that had previously operated on Phil came out to see the clean room and remarked that it was cleaner than his operating room.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 13)
  - "At Cliff's house with Cliff, Arch, Harold, and Pem" 1/4/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 12)
    She talks about the difficulty of understanding what Phil's patents actually mean. This mostly stems from the fact that patents name what they do, but not the context for what they do in a more complex combination.
    One of them remarks that they would sometimes doubt what he said but because his track record was so good they would go along with them regardless.
    She tells a story of being in Germany in 1939 and their uncomfortable experience because their sailings were cancelled repeatedly.
    They remark that the difficulty in writing the biography for Pem is not finding out when Phil was doing things, but finding out how that timeline related to other companies and individuals.
    They talk about some of the early processes they used and developed.
  - "Steve Hafer in SLC" 6/19/75 Side 1 Part 1. (Track 13)
    She tells the same story about the still in Hollywood from Disc 11.
    She tells a story about people following his speaking tour, and people who followed him to each appearance he gave despite the fact that his speech was the same at each stop.
    She tells the story of RCA battling in 1937 in court with Phil over who had invented television first. They were able to call on Justin Tollman, who was his chemistry teacher as a freshman in high school in 1922.
    They were able to locate him and bring him to the deposition and he was able to accurately describe and write what Phil had told him about fifteen years earlier. RCA did not win the case and was awarded nothing, and Phil felt it was largely because of Justin Tollman.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 14)
  - "Steve Hafer in SLC" 6/19/75 Side 1 Part 2. (Track 13)
    Before Phil had a nervous breakdown in early 1941, he had licensed some of his television patents in order to not hold up the television industry as a whole.
    She felt that he was very unhappy with the way the financials of the industry worked and this put a great deal of stress on him.
  - "Steve Hafer in SLC" 6/19/75 Side 2. (Track 13)
    She reads a first draft of her speech to a ward. She speaks about life with Phil and their experiences together inside and out of the church. She talks about his loss of faith for a period, but also about how he worked and hoped for a better future for mankind. There are approximately five minutes of blank tape at the end of this.
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Arch at his home" 8/24/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 14)
    Cliff tells a story of German Reich post scientists came over to learn what they could about electron multipliers, sometime in the fall of 1934 or 1935. They disagreed on which type of multiplier was more effective, the box type or the screen type. He made examples of both and tested them which proved that the box type was indeed more effective.
    He says that in order to operate the pump, they needed liquid air. The only way he could get it was to take a train and a ferry to Emeryville and fill up a five liter container, and then bring it back.
    She tells a story of a man borrowing another's safety light and how it lead to one of them getting a 5000 volt shock. The man who was borrowing the light was fired and the other somehow survived it.
    Although he had more training than Phil, he said that he quickly found that Phil had an amazing penchant for coming up with ideas.
    She tells a story of a fire at the lab and the problems with firefighting. The lab had enough materials that were extremely sensitive to water that the fire was very difficult to get under control.
    Early pictures tended to be green because they used a mineral called willemite.
    There are approximately six minutes of empty space at the end of the track.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 15)
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Arch at his home" 8/24/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 14)
    She talks about more mishaps between tubes exploding and sulfuric acid eating through the floor into the motor business that was beneath them.
    They discuss which Mickey Mouse films they had, presumably for broadcasting of some sort.
    She describes some work Phil had done for a bean company. They had been having problems with including beans that were not good in their cans, so he developed something that would kick discolored beans off of the conveyor belt.
    She says that Phil often struggled to get away from work and because of this Cliff would invite him and her on fishing trips to get him outside and out of the lab.
    She tells a story of catching and mounting a 20 inch trout and says that people would look at her funny when they saw it because normally that wouldn't be big enough to mount.
    He says they ran out of money for three months in San Francisco while the backers were questioning the investment.
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Arch at his home" 8/24/75 Side 1 Part 1., 1975 (Track 15)
    They talk about losing the stock that they had bought in RCA to ITT at some point but it's not totally clear what caused this. Possibly Phil's company going under? Difficult to tell exactly what happened.
    One of the men kept resolution charts from the company on glass slides. They are all very excited about this. He also has a clip of Mary Pickford combing her hair which was the first thing they ever put on the television.
    Pem recounts an agreement that Phil came to with ATT where they would pay him for the use of his patents, but he did not have to pay them for the use of theirs, which was especially significant because they owned so many.
    They talk about a time where Phil was considering the use of a Black Widow web in the crosshairs of an optical system, because the web of a Black Widow is especially strong.
    Pem says that Phil was extremely upset when they returned to Fort Wayne in 1948 because much of their early stuff had been thrown away.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 16)
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Arch at his home" 8/24/75 Side 1 Part 2., 1975 (Track 15)
    Disc is blank, no audio.
  - "Cliff, Pem, and Arch at his home" 8/24/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 15)
  - "Agnes, Laura, Pem" 8/31/75 Side 1 Part 1., 1975 (Track 16)
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 17)
  - "Agnes, Laura, Pem" 8/31/75 Side 1 Part 2., 1975 (Track 16)
    Pem tells a story about Phil sending kids to sell kits to households. Phil left the company that he was working for at that time because the owner accused him of stealing money.
  - "Agnes, Laura, Pem" 8/31/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 16)
    The tape is all of people talking to each other, it sounds like they must be looking at photographs. They talk over each other and mostly remark about the photos. Because they aren't speaking specifically for the tape recorder, the context is not really explained and it's difficult to get much out of it.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 18)
  - "Agnes and Ethyl Rush" 9/1/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 17)
    Pem says that Phil's father was very interested in astronomy and was constantly studying it and this knowledge was passed on to Phil.
    Phil's father, Lewis, went on a mission after he had his children and his wife had a bad heart. He went without any money or extra clothes and was able to live off of the generosity of people. His first wife died and he then was married to a woman named Serena.
    Agnes recounts learning bad words from men who were around the house because they would use them to describe pigs.
    They tell a story about Phil being taken by a group of Native Americans to a ceremony after playing with a Native American boy. He later tried to find these Native Americans to help them, but was unable to locate them.
    Agnes says they spent two months together hunting squirrels one summer because the Native Americans would pay fifteen cents for a squirrel. She says that Phil had a bow and arrow with nails attached to the arrows.
    Algebra was taught to Phil by Mr. Wells, but Mr. Wells had a procedure done on his eyes that made him very uncomfortable. Because of this, Phil helped to teach both algebra one and two one year and received extra-credit for doing so.
    Agnes tells the story of Lincoln B. Farnsworth, who was born unable to really eat very well. They thought he would die but she felt that her father's blessing saved him.